Finding Aid for Henry Hitt Crane Papers 1902-1977
Bentley Historical Library, University of Michigan
- Sermon file, 1925-1958
  - Typescripts and reprints
    - Brotherhood or Else (Box 23)
    - Business at Bat (Box 23)
    - Business Coming of Age (Box 23)
    - Calm (Box 23)
    - Can a Nation Be Born Again? (Box 23)
    - Can We Love Our Enemies? (John Haynes Holmes) (Box 23)
    - Can We Still Believe in Humanity? (Box 23)
    - Can We Survive? (Box 23)
    - Caption on the Cross (Box 23)
    - Catch-Phrase Religion (Box 23)
    - Century's Change in Religion (Box 23)
    - Child Midst (Box 23)
    - Child is Born (Box 23)
    - Christ for the Crisis (Box 23)
    - Christian Church in Time of War (Box 23)
    - Christian Counterbalance (Box 23)
    - Christians in a Warring World (Box 23)
    - Christian's Private Accounting (Box 23)
    - Christian's Style (Box 23)
    - Christmas Christianity (Box 23)
    - Christmas Focus (Box 23)
    - Christmas Vision (Box 23)
    - Church of Tomorrow (Box 23)
    - Church Unity (Box 23)
    - City of Everywhere (Box 23)
    - Clear Thinking in Confused Times (Box 23)
    - Cogency of the Cross (Box 23)
    - College Evangelism (Box 23)
    - Come-Back (Box 23)
    - Commending Christianity to Youth (Box 23)
    - Community Fund (Box 23)
    - Company at the Cross (Box 23)
    - Contagious Christianity (Box 23)
    - Cross Bearer (Box 23)
    - Crossing the Deadline (Box 23)
    - Crucial Question of Peacetime Conscription (Box 23)
    - Crush of the Crowd (Box 23)
    - Dare We Look at Our World? (Box 23)
    - Decalogue for Parents (Box 23)
    - Decalogue of Disciplines for Clear Thinking in Confused Times (Box 23)
    - Declaration of Faith (Box 23)
    - Delusions (Box 23)
    - Democracy lectures 1940 (Box 23)
    - Democracy, The Meaning of (Box 23)
    - Democracy, The Principles of, Applied to Wealth (Box 23)
    - Disciplining our Dispositions (Box 23)
    - Divided Against Themselves (Box 23)
    - Divine Demand for Desegregation (Box 23)
    - Divinely Undrugged (Box 23)
    - Divinity of Christ (Box 23)
    - Do All Things Work for Good? (Box 23)
    - Does It Pay to Be Honest? (Box 23)
    - Dragon of Omi-Fugi (Box 23)
    - Dreams and Ideals (Box 23)
    - Easter: Revelation of Reality (Box 23)
    - Educated Heart (Box 23)
    - Enduring to the End (Box 23)
    - Escape or Encounter (Box 23)
    - Eternal Life (Box 23)
    - European trip 1948 (Box 23)
      articles/messages written about
    - Evangelism of Emphasis (Box 23)
    - Excuses (Box 23)
    - Eye of the Soul (Box 23)
    - Fable of the Forest (Box 23)
    - Facing the New Year (Box 23)
    - Faith, A Healing Factor (Box 23)
    - Faith, The Foundation of Freedom (Box 23)
    - Faith that Works (Box 23)
    - Fascism, Nazism & European Democracy (Box 23)
    - Field of the Fool (Box 23)
    - Fiercest Fight of the War (Box 23)
    - Fight Like Hell (Box 23)
    - Finding the Value of "X" in "Xmas" (Box 23)
    - First Murderer (Box 23)
    - Friendship, Seven Laws of (Box 23)
    - Flame of Friendship (Box 23)
    - For Such a Time as This (Box 23)
    - Four-Fold Function of Faith (Box 23)
    - Four Things (Box 23)
    - Fourth Companion (Box 23)
    - Friends, If--- (Box 23)
    - Gamblers All (Box 23)
    - Gambling, The Evil of (Box 23)
    - Gandhi, My Hour with Mahatma Gandhi (Box 23)
    - Ghosts (Box 23)
    - Ghost Story (Box 23)
    - Giving Childhood Its Chance (Box 23)
    - God Prays (Box 23)
    - God's Eyes (Box 23)
    - God's Intolerable Compliment (Box 23)
    - God's Peace Proposal (Box 23)
    - God's Smile (Box 23)
    - Good Die Young (Box 23)
    - Gospel According to You (Box 23)
    - Gospel of Good Healing (Box 23)
    - Great Refusal (Box 23)
    - Greatest Lie in the World (Box 23)
    - Guests at the Inn (Box 23)
    - Haunted by Angels (Box 23)
    - Healing of Hate (Box 23)
    - He Knew What was in Man (Box 23)
    - Heads Up! (Box 23)
    - Heart of the Home (Box 23)
    - Hell and Final Judgment (Box 23)
    - Hero and the Handicap (Box 23)
    - Hidden Persuaders (Box 23)
    - Higher Intoxication (Box 23)
    - Hitting the Heel (The Vulnerable Spot) (Box 23)
    - Honesty (Box 23)
    - House of God (Box 23)
    - How Can We Know What's True? (Box 23)
    - How High are Your Hopes? (Box 23)
    - How Much do You Owe Yourself? (Box 23)
    - How Shall We Think of Man? (Box 23)
    - How We Fool Ourselves (Box 23)
    - Human Heart of God (Box 23)
    - I Know that My Redeemer Liveth (Box 23)
    - If a Man Die, Shall he Live Again? (Box 23)
    - Immortality (Box 23)
    - Incredible India (Box 23)
    - Indispensable Fellowship (Box 23)
    - In Hoc Signo Vinces (Box 23)
    - Inner Glow (Box 23)
    - Inverted Thanksgivings (Box 23)
    - Invisible Walls (Box 23)
    - Iron Beds in the Modern Manner (Box 23)
    - Is Morality Legality? (Box 23)
    - Is the Social Gospel Out of Date? (Box 23)
    - It is Finished (Box 23)
    - J.D. James, The Most Unusual Layman of My Experience (Box 23)
    - Japan, Earthquakes and God (Box 23)
    - Japanese Incident (Box 23)
    - Jew, Catholic and Protestant (Box 23)
    - Job for the Angels (Box 23)
    - Joy of the Job (Box 23)
    - Justice, The Basis of Brotherhood (Box 24)
    - Kingdom of God (Box 24)
    - Last Full Measure of Devotion (Box 24)
    - Lest We Forget (Box 24)
    - Lies that Blind (Box 24)
    - Life's Detours (Box 24)
    - Lift Up Your Hearts (Box 24)
    - Light, Liberty, Life (Box 24)
    - Like a Tree (Box 24)
    - Living by Luck or by Law (Box 24)
    - Lonely, The (Box 24)
    - Lord's Prayer messages (Box 24)
    - Loving Life is Living Love (Box 24)
    - Making the Best of the Worst (Box 24)
    - Marks of a Christian (Box 24)
    - Man is Known by the Company He Keeps (Box 24)
    - Matchless Mother (Box 24)
    - Meaning and Objectives of Marriage (Box 24)
    - Meet the Mob Mind (Box 24)
    - Men Versus Mountains (Box 24)
    - Merits of Madness (Box 24)
    - Message of the Resurrection (Box 24)
    - Might and Menace of the U.S.S.R. (Box 24)
    - Might of the Mite (Box 24)
    - Mighty Meek (Box 24)
    - Miller, Marie (reported sermons) (Box 24)
    - Miscellaneous, 9 folders (Box 24)
      (include excerpts, drafts, summaries, notes, radio and other addresses, etc.)
    - Modern Relevance of Protestant Principles (Box 24)
    - Modernizing Memorial Day (Box 24)
    - Money Talks (Box 24)
    - Most Notorious Liar (Box 24)
    - Mother Heart of the World (Box 24)
    - Mother India Cradles Religion (Box 24)
    - Music Makers in a Discordant World (Box 24)
    - My Novel (Box 24)
    - Mystery of Coincidence (Box 24)
    - McConaughy (James) Inauguration (Wesleyan University) (Box 24)
    - Narrowness of the Christian Way (Box 24)
    - Near View of the Far East (Box 24)
    - Necessity of Sacrifice (Box 24)
    - New Liberalism and Morals (Box 24)
    - New Light on an Old Problem (Box 24)
    - New Years Explorations-In Religions (Box 24)
    - Niemoeller (Martin) (Box 24)
      (HHC report on address of, 1947)
    - Not for Sale (Box 24)
    - Oil for the Lamps of Education (Box 24)
    - Old Folks (Box 24)
    - On Becoming World Citizens (Box 24)
    - On Being a Good Sport (Box 24)
    - On Being a Thoroughbred (Box 24)
    - On Being Open-Minded (Box 24)
    - On Being Human (Box 24)
    - On Entering the Promised World (Box 24)
    - On Preaching Unpopular Truth (Box 24)
    - On Remembering the Dead (Box 24)
    - On to V.F. Day (Box 24)
    - Our Faith in Christ (Box 24)
    - Our Faith in God (Box 24)
    - Our Faith in Immorality (Box 24)
    - Our Faith in Love (Box 24)
    - Our Faith in Prayer (Box 24)
    - Our Faith in the Bible (Box 24)
    - Our Faith in the Holy Spirit (Box 24)
    - Our Fateful Failure (Box 24)
    - Our Father (Box 24)
      (see also Lord's Prayer messages)
    - Our Fourfold Faith (Box 24)
    - Our Futile Flight from God (Box 24)
    - Our Paramount Predicament (Box 24)
    - Our Search for Security (Box 24)
    - Our Spiritual Forebears (Box 24)
    - Our Toughest Task (Box 24)
    - Out into the Deep (Box 24)
    - Overcoming the World by Faith (Box 24)
    - Palms, the Cross and the Crown (Box 24)
    - Parable for Election Day (Box 24)
    - Paradox of the Passion (Box 24)
    - Paul, the Man (Box 24)
    - Peace and the Power Problem (Box 24)
    - Peacetime Conscription-"For God and Country" (Box 24)
    - Persistent Problems of Normal People (Box 24)
    - Pioneering in Prayer (Box 24)
    - Platinum Principle (Box 24)
    - Power and Purpose of God (Box 24)
    - Power of Public Opinion (Box 24)
    - Prayer- December 14, 1941 (Box 24)
      (includes message "Christians in a Warring World")
    - Prayer: A Healing Power (Box 24)
    - Prayer Power (Box 24)
    - Praying for the Sick (Box 24)
    - Preaching Unpopular Truths (Box 24)
    - Prescription for Forgiveness (Box 24)
    - Problem of Achieving Maturity (Box 24)
    - Problem of Achieving Success (Box 24)
    - Problem of Being an Odd Fellow (Box 24)
    - Problem of Being a Somebody (Box 24)
    - Problem of Discouragement (Box 24)
    - Problem of Escape (Box 24)
    - Problem of Fear (Box 24)
    - Problem of Frustration (Box 24)
    - Problem of Getting What We Deserve (Box 24)
    - Problem of Happiness (Box 24)
    - Problem of Home Building (Box 24)
    - Problem of Inadequacy (Box 24)
    - Problem of Love (Box 24)
    - Problem of Means and Ends (Box 25)
    - Problem of Parents (Box 25)
    - Problem of Popularity (Box 25)
    - Problem of Prejudice (Box 25)
    - Problem of Propagating Christianity (Box 25)
    - Problem of Suffering (Box 25)
    - Problem of the Unmarried (Box 25)
    - Prodigal Daughters (Box 25)
    - Prohibition-A Moral Issue (Box 25)
    - Public Friend No. 1 (Box 25)
    - Pursuit of Happiness (Box 25)
    - Quest for the Best (Box 25)
    - Rainbow in the Cloud (Box 25)
    - Reach of Reason and Feel of Faith (Box 25)
    - Real Problem of Reconversion (Box 25)
    - Real Labor Problem (Box 25)
    - Realities (Box 25)
    - Realizing the Resurrection (Box 25)
    - Reconstruction of Personality (Box 25)
    - Requirements of Real Religion (Box 25)
    - Resurrection (Box 25)
    - Rich Fool (Box 25)
    - Right to be Inspired (Box 25)
    - River of God (Box 25)
    - Romance of Retirement (Box 25)
    - Roosevelt Night 1923 (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Business (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Civilization (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Happiness (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Home (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Parenthood (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Reality (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Reverence (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Sovereignty (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Truth (Box 25)
    - Safeguard of Worship (Box 25)
    - Salute to Youth (Box 25)
    - Scientists and Religionists Get Together (Box 25)
    - Sell-Out (Box 25)
    - Separators (Box 25)
    - Sermons (books of the Bible)
      - Acts (Box 25)
      - Epistles (Box 25)
      - John (Box 25)
      - Mark (Box 25)
      - Matthew (Box 25)
      - New Testament (Box 25)
      - Old Testament, 2 folders (Box 25)
    - Shall We Let Them Starve? (Box 25)
    - Sights and Insights of Europe (Box 25)
    - Sin of Belatedness (Box 25)
    - Sky-Gazers-Then and Now (Box 25)
    - Song for Your Soul (Box 25)
    - Stable and the Star (Box 25)
    - Steps-Up or Down (Box 25)
    - Stand for Something or Fall for Anything (Box 25)
    - Stewardship of Time (Box 25)
    - Strategy of Sacrifice (Box 25)
    - Strength from the Stars (Box 25)
    - Struggle Within Ourselves (Box 25)
    - Successful Marriage (Box 25)
    - Swords and Ploughshares in Palestine (Box 25)
    - Supreme Resolve for the New Year (Box 25)
    - Sympathetic Touch (Box 25)
    - Taking Care of Our Own (Box 25)
    - Taking the Cross Seriously (Box 25)
    - Taking Inventory of Oneself (Box 25)
    - Tale of Two Cities (Box 25)
    - Teacher (Box 25)
    - Technique of Tolerance (Box 25)
    - Technique of Triumph (Box 25)
    - Ten Christian Commandments (Box 25)
    - Ten Commandments series (Box 25)
      (also filed as "Safeguard" messages)
    - Thanksgiving (Box 25)
    - Thermometers vs. Thermostats (Box 25)
    - They Shall Not Starve (Box 25)
    - Three Immortal Imperatives (Box 25)
    - This Ambiguous Struggle (Box 25)
    - Thoughts for the Time of Sorrow (Box 25)
    - Thunder, Angels and God (Box 25)
    - Tide of Religion (Box 25)
    - Tide of Tomorrow (Box 25)
    - Time to Laugh (Box 25)
    - Time to Pray (Box 25)
    - Tide is Sure to Win (Box 25)
    - Tone of the Voice (Box 25)
    - Totems and Taboos (Box 25)
    - Towel Test (Box 25)
    - Traits of the Twentieth Century Pioneer (Box 25)
    - Trial of Jesus (Box 25)
    - Trouble Woman (Box 25)
    - True Challenge of this Hour (Box 25)
    - Twenty-third Psalm (Box 25)
    - Typical Traitor (Box 25)
    - Ultimate Victory (Box 25)
    - Unconscious Sins (Box 25)
    - Under Pressure (Box 25)
    - Undisputed Passage (Box 25)
    - Unknown Soldier Speaks (Box 25)
    - Unveiling the Dark Continent (Box 25)
    - Use of Holy Silence (Box 25)
    - Valiant Behavior (Box 25)
    - Valiant New Year (Box 25)
    - Vicious Virtues (Box 25)
    - Vision and Task (Box 25)
    - Voyagers (Box 25)
    - Watch (Box 25)
    - What are Christians? (Box 25)
    - What are Christian Liberals? (Box 25)
    - What Do you Expect in circa 1947 (Box 25)
    - What is Democracy? (Box 25)
    - What's Most Worthwhile? (Box 25)
    - What on Earth is God Doing? (Box 25)
    - Who Cares? (Box 25)
    - Which Way to Peace? (Box 25)
    - Whither Bound America? (Box 25)
    - Why Be Thankful (Box 25)
    - Why So Afraid of the Future (Box 25)
    - Why Christ? (Box 25)
    - Why Capital Punishment? (Box 25)
    - Why I Entered the Ministry (other pastors) (Box 25)
    - Will of God series (Box 25)
    - Wings (Box 25)
    - Wonder of Christmas (Box 25)
    - World Wide Communion (Box 25)
    - Wrath of God (Box 25)
    - Wrestlers (Box 25)
    - "Xmas" (Box 25)
    - You-In Person (Box 25)
    - Your Rendezvous with Life (Box 25)
    - Zacchaeusites (Box 25)
  - Notecards
    (arranged alphabetically by sermon title; notecards list dates and place given of the message; also notes for message as used from the pulpit)
    - A-P (Box 26-a)
    - P-Z (Box 26-b)
  - Notecards listing salary and payment received for speeches, etc. 1925-1966 (Box 26-b)
  - Notecards (Box 26-b)
    (alphabetical by city listing date, place, title of message, etc.)
  - Miscellaneous notecards (Box 26-b)
  - Sound recordings of sermons and other speeches (Box 27)
  - Sound recordings of sermons and other speeches (Box 28)
    (continued)
  - Sound recordings of sermons and other speeches (Box 29)
- Scrapbooks, 12 volumes
  Scrapbooks, 1928-1958, consists of twelve volumes and one folder of newspaper clippings about Crane and his ministry. There are also clippings of newspaper articles that Crane wrote for Detroit newspapers.
  - 1928-1958 (Box 30)
  - Newspaper articles written by HHC 1936-1937 (Box 30)
- Church Bulletins and Newsletters (from churches where HHC pastored)
  The Church Bulletins and Newsletters series consists of 35 volumes of the bulletins (called schedule of service) and published newsletters from the churches pastored by Crane from 1926 to 1958.
  - 1926-1945, 20 volumes (Box 31)
  - 1945-1958, 15 volumes (Box 32)
- Visual Materials
  Visual Materials is the smallest series. There are two folders of photographs consisting of images of Crane, either portraits, with his family, as part of groups of which he was a member, or in the pulpit. There is also a motion picture film of Crane speaking on the topic of pacifism and the Cold War. The film has been digitized and is available on DVD or as a streaming file.
  - Photographs, 1 folders (Box 32)
  - Photographs 1952-1961, undated (Box 32)
  - Motion Picture
    - Henry Hitt Crane speech on pacifism and the Cold War undated, 85164-1
      - Original:, 16mm film, b/w, pos, optical, 00:44:43
        [Restricted]
      - Use Copy:, DVD (Box 1)
      - Streaming File: 85164-1, flash-flv
    - Unidentified film (Box 32)
- Retirement Files
  The final series, Retirement Files, date mostly from the six years following Crane's retirement in 1958. In addition to small files of sermons, writings, and correspondence, the series contains pamphlets, fliers and programs announcing Crane's sermons and guest lectures at churches across the country. Another file consists primarily of news clippings relating to sermons, peace marches, and other protest activities in which Crane participated.
  - Clippings
    - Controversial Appearance in Butte, Montana 1960 (Box 33)
    - General 1959-1965, undated (Box 33)
    - Local Appearances 1956-1963, undated (Box 33)
    - Personal 1955-1977, undated (Box 33)
    - Retirement 1958-1959, undated (Box 33)
  - Correspondence 1958-1960, undated
    - General 1959-1960, undated (Box 33)
    - Search for Dr. Crane's Successor 1958 (Box 33)
  - Programs and Pamphlets 1959-1964, undated, 2 folders (Box 33)
  - Retirement Testimonial 1958 (Box 33)
  - Sermons and a Wedding Ceremony 1960, 1965, 1967 undated (Box 33)
  - Writings 1940, 1958-1959, 1966 undated
    - "Is the Social Gospel Out-of-Date," 1958 (Box 33)
    - Miscellaneous 1958, 1966 undated (Box 33)
    - Poems 1940 undated (Box 33)
    - "The Romance of Retirement," 1958-1959 (Box 33)